Postdoctoral Candidate in Bioinformatics

Paul-Arthur MESLIN

Ph.D. student in Bioinformatics

18 rue Étienne Dolet, Cachan, 94230

+33688921719 paul-arthur.meslin@inserm.fr

https://github.com/PaulArthurM

https://github.com/PaulArthurM	
Research interests	
I am currently completing my PhD in bioinformatics, with a focus on the analysis of single-cell time-ser research primarily involves temporally resolved lineage tracing, aiming to better understand cellular proof. The goal of my research is to contribute to a deeper understanding of cellular dynamics, particularly response to treatment and disease progression.	ocesses over time.
Education	
Ph.D. in Bioinformatics (on going) Université Paris Cité, Paris, France Supervisor: Dr. Camille Lobry	2021-2024 (expected)
 M.Sc. in Bioinformatics, Modelling and Statistics Université Rouen Normandie, Rouen, France M2 in apprenticeship for 2 years: 50% in the laboratory, 50% at school. 	2018-2021
 B.Sc. in Biochemistry, Molecular and Cellular Biology and Physiology Université Rouen Normandie, Rouen, France Basis of experimental biology, biochemistry, molecular and cellular biology, physiology and genetics. 	2015-2018
Experience	
Ph.D. Student, UMR 7212 / Inserm U944, Université Paris Cité, France Supervisor: Dr. Camille Lobry - Analyzed time-series single-cell RNA-seq data to trace cell lineage in acute myeloid leukemia studies.	2021-2024 (expected)
M2 Apprentice, UMR 7212 / Inserm U944, Université Paris Cité, France Supervisors: Dr. Alexandre Puissant, Dr. Camille Lobry - Developed 'PitViper', a software tool for meta-analysis and annotation in functional genomic screening - Investigated genomic instability by analyzing NGS data, contrasting normal and tumor pairs in AML ca	2019-2021 ases.
M1 Intern, UMR 7212 / Inserm U944, Gustave Roussy, France Supervisor: Dr. Camille Lobry - Integrated ChIP-seq and RNA-seq datasets to identify and characterize super-enhancers in genomic study	March-Sept. 2019 dies.
L3 Intern, Inserm U918, Centre Henri Becquerel, Rouen, France Supervisor: Dr. Pierre-Julien Viailly - Evaluated and optimized existing pipelines for enhanced next-generation sequencing data processing.	April 2018
L2 Voluntary Intern, TIBS team, LITIS, Université de Rouen Normandie, France Supervisor: Dr. Arnaud Lefebvre - Engineered a web application to dynamically visualize mass spectrometry data outcomes, enhancing dat	May-June 2017 a interpretability.
Publications	
-Lin KH, Rutter JC, Xie A, et al. P2RY2-AKT activation is a therapeutically actionable consequinhibition in acute myeloid leukemia. Nat Cancer. (2022) -Fenwarth L et al. A personalized approach to guide allogeneic stem cell transplantation in	

with acute myeloid leukemia. Blood. (2021)

Key Skills
Programming and Data Analysis: Advanced proficiency in Python and R for statistical modeling, data manipulation, and visualization; Bash.
Bioinformatics Tools: Extensive experience with severse ecosystem (scanpy, anndata, cellrank, sevi-tools).
Data Visualization: Skilled in creating informative visual representations of complex datasets using tools such as matplotlib, ggplot2, plotly and seaborn.
Reproducible Research: Committed to reproducibility using version control systems (Git, GitHub), containerization (Docker), and workflow management tools (Snakemake with Conda).
Machine Learning: Familiar with pytorch and scikit-learn and related Python libraries for implementing machine learning algorithms in biological data analysis.
Teaching
Bioinformatics Master's Student Association Tutoring Coordinator, Rouen, France - Provide individualized Python programming and Linux tutoring to M1 students.
Conferences
Bioinfo Single Cell Seminar, Institut Curie, Paris - Presentation of my thesis project at a single-cell seminar
Journées Ouvertes en Biologie, Informatique et Mathématiques (JOBIM), Rennes - Presentation of a poster on PitViper
Public Engagement
Dialogues Entre Chercheurs et Lycéens pour les Intéresser à la Construction des Savoirs 2023 - Dialogues with high school students to arouse their interest in the development of knowledge and fundamental research.
Languages
French: Native
English: Intermediate
Norwegian: Beginner, following Norwegian language and culture courses at the Maison de Norvège in Paris
References
Dr. Camille Lobry, Principal Investigator, Inserm U944, Université Paris Cité, France

Dr. Alexandre Puissant, Principal Investigator, Inserm U944, Université Paris Cité, France